<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Theory and history - Michael McCall</title><link href="https://www.mccall.cc/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.mccall.cc/feeds/michael-mccall.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.mccall.cc/</id><updated>2019-04-04T01:01:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Reflections on the American PhD admissions process</title><link href="https://www.mccall.cc/19_Admissions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-04T01:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-04T01:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Michael McCall</name></author><id>tag:www.mccall.cc,2019-04-04:/19_Admissions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having completed more PhD applications than I really want to count (primarily, though not exclusively based in the US), I hope that I can provide a few informed suggestions based on my experience as an applicant. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not graduate from a particularly prestigous university, but I definitely recognize that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having completed more PhD applications than I really want to count (primarily, though not exclusively based in the US), I hope that I can provide a few informed suggestions based on my experience as an applicant. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not graduate from a particularly prestigous university, but I definitely recognize that I had one major advantage that many do not: a bit of extra cash to could burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my perspective, I conceptually seperate the application components into two major categories: internal and external documents. Internal documents I can produce myself, namely the statement of purpose, my CV, my personal information and basic education history. External documents, on the other hand, require external processes to deliver a final product to the graduate admissions department, such as GRE scores (ETS), transcripts (registrar’s offices), and letters of recommendations (recommenders). I can confidently state that 99% of my application-related financial externalities and personal stress was inflicted by elements falling into the latter category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each external process introduces an additional monetary burden, a demand on a third party, or both. In short, the thrust of my recommendations would be to &lt;strong&gt;reduce reliance on external processes &lt;em&gt;at the point of application&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, as each one adds to the inefficency of an already cumbersome process when scaled up. Considering how rapidly these costs in time and money accumulate as the numbers of applications increase, I cannot ignore how my seemingly minor privilege translates into a very tangible advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To break down some of these barriers, I hope to make a few short, non-revolutionary and practical suggestions on how to mitigate these burdens, ranked roughly according to feasibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accept unofficial GRE scores&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, students get four free GRE score reports. I’d wager that most applicants aren’t only applying to four departments, though. Each ASR (Additional Score Report, their initialism) from ETS runs for $27, which, for ten applications, adds up to an additional $167. If online forums are to be believed, I’ve seen people who have applied to over 22 departments, which adds nearly $500 to an applicant’s bill. Is this a flagrant violation of a price signal that seems designed to limit the number of applications? Sure, but that’s the advantage that the wealthy enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GRE scores should be one of the easiest elements of the application to submit, based on their brevity alone. ETS even offers online PDF printouts of scores, which some departments do request, but only to verify your registration number. The best mechanism for GRE submission I saw personally was, hands down, from University of Virginia, with three individual number entry fields within the application where the applicant could enter their verbal, quantitative and analytical writing scores. These were accepted unofficially under the assumption that the official scores would be forthcoming from ETS if accepted, and were sent and verified prior to matriculation. Simple, straightforward perfection. I feel like the playing field would be leveled significantly if more departments adopted this practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unofficial trascripts are accepted by the majority of universities already under this same assumption, and it seems wholly feasible for GRE scores to be given similar treatment with minimal impact on the overall application process. And for those universities that don’t accept unofficial transcripts…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accept unofficial transcripts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably ranks higher than #1 in regards to feasibility. Only a few departments still require the submission of official transcript at the point of application, but the practice remains prevalent enough to warrant reiterating that this poses an unnessessary hurdle to applicants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am likely a rare case in this respect, but my entire postsecondary educational record comprises five seperate transcripts from three different countries. Submitting these five transcripts is trivial and instant to do if unofficial transcripts suffice. Submitting official copies, on the other hand, is a process that involves both bureaucratic navigation, fees between $5-25 per copy, and potentially 4 or more weeks to arrive from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Utilize dossier services for letters of recommendation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard from some of my friends from more well-to-do departments that faculty are willing to submit on their behalf letters of recommendation for twenty applications with one week’s notice. Alas, I am not endowed with such blessings, and furthermore, I cannot fathom asking another human being to wrestle with twenty seperate archaic university application systems on an immovable deadline. Professors are busy people, and after a recommender writes the letter, their job should be done. This problem is imperfectly solved through the growing acceptance of Interfolio, which seems to be becoming the de facto standard. I have to admit, I am one happy customer of this service. The two major practical issues with Interfolio, however, are a lack of universal acceptance and the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost itself is not as prohibitive as GRE scores and transcript fees, as the annual package available for $50 is probably sufficient for most applicant cases. Out of all the potential extras involved in the graduate application process, I would consider subscribing to Interfolio to have been the best value for money. The principle itself is troubling, though: those who are able to pay the fee are freed from what I found to be the single most time consuming part of the application process: following up on letters of recommendation requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if one does subscribe to Interfolio, however, lack of universal acceptance presents another artifical barrier to selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankly, as a millennial, I feel like I stumble across the ghosts of a previously robust system that once existed every time I scan the FAQ section of many Political Science departments. I am not exactly sure what role a Career Services office once played in terms of acting as a dossier manager, but it looks like we once had a more ideal solution that distributed the academic labor appropriately. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>